<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>SAA 2018 Government Digital Data</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/</id><updated>2018-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Sharing Curation Expertise and Space for Digital Archaeological and Cultural Heritage Data</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/curation-ellison-mcmanamon.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Leigh Anne Ellison</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-04-07:/SAA2018digigovt/curation-ellison-mcmanamon.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="leigh.ellison@asu.edu"&gt;Leigh Anne Ellison&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="fpmcmanamon@asu.edu"&gt;Francis Pierce-McManamon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists are busy all the time. Often stretching to meet a variety of professional obligations.  CRM and government agency archaeologists are among the most stretched given the different directions that pull upon their professional lives. Scholarly pursuits; administrative, bureaucratic, regulatory, and public outreach responsibilities …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="leigh.ellison@asu.edu"&gt;Leigh Anne Ellison&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="fpmcmanamon@asu.edu"&gt;Francis Pierce-McManamon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists are busy all the time. Often stretching to meet a variety of professional obligations.  CRM and government agency archaeologists are among the most stretched given the different directions that pull upon their professional lives. Scholarly pursuits; administrative, bureaucratic, regulatory, and public outreach responsibilities related to physical sites and collections, easily fill or over-fill their schedules. Now the care and curation of digital data adds to the piling up of responsibilities. Digital data and the technical tools that create and enable its use present many opportunities for research and resource management. Digital technology makes data easily and widely accessible, sharing information, and enabling the creation of new interpretations and increase in overall knowledge. But, digital data must be curated or it will be lost. Digital curation doesn’t just happen, it requires attention, special expertise, and long-term commitment to the curation enterprise. The Digital Archaeological Record (tDAR) is a repository where individual archaeologists, agencies, and organizations deposit their data (e.g., documents, images, data sets, and more). Once deposited in tDAR the data are curated by digital archival specialists who focus on ensuring the data are protected, made available as the depositor determines, and kept available for use and re-use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_1.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_2.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_3.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_4.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_5.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_6.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_7.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_8.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_9.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_10.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_11.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_12.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_13.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_14.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_15.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_16.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_17.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_18.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_19.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_20.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_21.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_22.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_23.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_24.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_25.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_26.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_27.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_28.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_29.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_30.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_31.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_32.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_33.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_34.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_35.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_36.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_36.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ellison and McManamon" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Ellison_McManamon_36.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data"></category><category term="repositories"></category><category term="curation"></category></entry><entry><title>Always Halfway There: Keeping Up with Digital Archaeological Data in Virginia</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/halfway-smith.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jolene Smith</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-04-07:/SAA2018digigovt/halfway-smith.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="jolene.smith@dhr.virginia.gov"&gt;Jolene Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since being one of the first State Historic Preservation Offices to adopt electronic records management in the late ‘80s, the Virginia Department of Historic Resources has worked through several iterations of databases and web applications. These systems manage basic site information, details about physical collections, and now digital …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="jolene.smith@dhr.virginia.gov"&gt;Jolene Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since being one of the first State Historic Preservation Offices to adopt electronic records management in the late ‘80s, the Virginia Department of Historic Resources has worked through several iterations of databases and web applications. These systems manage basic site information, details about physical collections, and now digital media and datasets themselves. Over time, the agency’s priorities and objectives surrounding digital records and data have evolved in ways common to other institutions. As the most recent web GIS and database application reaches mid-life after four years, a thorough assessment of current and ideal approaches to digital data curation, preservation, and distribution is coming due as planning begins for what comes next. Building from concepts in libraries and archives, informatics, and data science, this presentation explores possible road maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Smith Title Slide" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Smith_1.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Jolene Smith. Since 2008, I’ve managed archaeological sites data at the Virginia Department of Historic Resources  (DHR), the State Historic Preservation Office (the SHPO). In Virginia, we’ve got about 45,000 sites recorded in the statewide inventory, with more added every day that I’m at my desk. This presentation is from my perspective at DHR, but it doesn't necessarily reflect the priorities of my agency as a whole.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We the site file managers are &lt;a href="http://themaintainers.org/"&gt;Maintainers&lt;/a&gt;. Few, if any, of us are formally trained in library science, archives, or database architecture. Mostly, we seem to identify as archaeologists, even if it’s been a while since we’ve sunk our trowels into soil. The archaeological data that we ingest, curate, and preserve are extensions of the physical, material record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of our work is that it's never done. We're adding new data and looking for novel ways to organize and use it, but we're also in a perpetual state of organizing, tidying, aligning, and adapting our collections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our voluminous archaeological sites dataset is only part of the story. In the Virginia Cultural Resource Information System (our online inventory database), we've got another 200,000 "architectural" records.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;   The archaeological and architectural records are like apples and oranges, and VCRIS is the fruit basket. This presentation is about archaeology, but this kind of context is helpful for understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where We've Been&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While most systematic data collection began with the passing of the National Historic Preservation Act of 1966 and the establishment of the Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission (which would later evolve into the Virginia Department of Historic Resources), the first "official" archaeology records in Virginia were created through the State Library. In 1927, the Virginia State Commission of Conservation and Development established the Division of History and Archaeology. Shortly thereafter, division member E.B. Sacrey established the Archeological Society of Virginia (2004 Library of Virginia). In 1962, the State Library appointed Howard MacCord the first State Archaeologist  (2009 Council of Virginia Archaeologists). All this is to say we've been amassing archaeological information through state government for quite some time here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 50 years since the advent of the State Historic Preservation Office (SHPO), we've seen tremendous change, both in volume of records and in technology to make them accessible. In Virginia, records for archaeological resources are managed along side records for above-ground architectural properties. Today, our collection includes about 45,000 archaeological records and 200,000 architectural records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1991 the agency began using IPS (Integrated Preservation Software), an offline relational database developed with the National Park Service and distributed between individuals and institutions and then manually synced as needed. For the first time, archaeological site records were digitized, although only new work. NPS encouraged new kinds of multi-state analysis and new ways to use information and envisioned large-scale data analysis possibilities using a standardized system (Miller 1994), however IPS did not become widely adopted across states (Smith 2016).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A printout of an IPS record and a floppy disk." src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Smith_2.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the late 1990s through early 2000s, DHR staff and contractors transcribed all basic site-level information from paper records and migrated IPS data into the new Historic Resources Data Sharing System (DSS), one of the first web databases in the country with comprehensive state archaeological site data. For the first time, users had access to statewide information with querying power and a full web GIS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A screenshot of the Data Sharing System" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Smith_3.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our technological infrastructure reached the end of its supported life, we began the process of building a completely new custom application through a vendor, VCRIS (the Virginia Cultural Resource Information System). As part of the development process, we re-modeled data structures and migrated terms.
In 2013, DHR deployed the system with a new, more powerful web database and map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A screenshot of VCRIS" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Smith_4.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What worked:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geospatial ingest directly from users (resulting in no more hours of heads-up digitizing graphic maps on my part) and strict data entry conditions dramatically improved many parts of our records management workflow. An ESRI feature service allowed us to reduce distribution of static geospatial data, a security risk and an invitation to make mistakes with old data. Tiered access to the system allowed for differential access (data entry, just architecture, or both archaeology and architecture), enabling us to keep a tighter handle on sensitive site locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Room for Improvement&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our initial vision aimed for a system that would allow for much more internal collaboration by DHR staff, a goal that was only partially realized. In the old way, the flow of information tends to come in for the most part from outside consultants and Archives staff quality control and maintain the data. We've not yet succeeded in integrating key pieces of management information like National Register eligibility concurrence as it's created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We initially planned on integrating "file attachments" into each record, to contain digital media related to each site and property. However, some introspection and research into digital preservation and assets led us to the conclusion that we needed to slow down and consider more robust infrastructure for our digital archives in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to grapple with data migration issues originating from transcription and transformation between several different databases over decades. For example, we discovered that, for archaeological records in DSS, the reports made certain fields &lt;em&gt;appear&lt;/em&gt; related, when in fact there was no true relationship in the database. Some of this cleanup we can do programmatically, but many relationships are highly subjective and require an expert decision to make a site classification or cultural affiliation. All of this makes querying from the front end very difficult (or misleading), and is compounded by some major deficiencies in the query interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCRIS was developed according to a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model"&gt;waterfall model&lt;/a&gt; of project management. While the philosophy aligned well with government procurement processes, it made iterating through rough spots and making improvements nearly impossible. We are five years into the use of this system and we still have hundreds of items on our "fix" list. However, we changed gears, using an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development"&gt;agile&lt;/a&gt; approach and are adapting contract schedules to tie into bite-sized goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've also got voluminous collection of media, in various states of digitization. Many photos, slides, and reports have been scanned, but not all. Some were scanned long ago at a resolution that's no longer adequate. Key metadata are stored in filenames in a standardized format, but only to a very low level of detail. We've got some major digital archives work to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;/box of legacy media photo/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The next thing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until recently, those of us on the VCRIS team still felt like it was relatively shiny and new. And then a developer broke the news that our baby was officially middle-aged. After we spat out our coffee, we immediately started planning for what is to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of critical importance moving forward for our agency and others is to begin to explode the data silos that we all maintain. Research information, catalogs of our physical collection containing ~8 million artifacts, management and regulatory actions, tracking of preservation easements, and other data produced and maintained between divisions needs to be interoperable and connected. But should we invest in One Application to Rule Them All?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I argue that it might not be a great idea. Funding is often tied to a fiscal year and can be unpredictable from one year to the next. This makes taking on a huge, integrated project a risky endeavor for a small public agency. From a technical standpoint, adopting independent but connected platforms that allow for pragmatic mix-and-match of open source, proprietary "off the shelf," and custom solutions can get us far. We operate in a low-resource environment. Budgets are always tight and access to I.T. expertise can be hard to come by. By being realistic about this from the outset, we can create more durable and flexible systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Digital media preservation and access&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development of a digital media repository is a top priority for the very near future. Like many other agencies, undoubtedly, collection of digital media has been a secondary endeavor. We're just now reaching a juncture where most of what we take in is "born digital" and not a scanned surrogate of a hardcopy object. As archives paraprofessionals, we've been working hard to obtain solid knowledge and understanding of digital preservation and access concepts to bring us up to speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Competing priorities or a false dichotomy?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of any planning and development process, we have to figure out what our applications need to do. What functionality serves our mission? What's very interesting, but probably out-of scope? While budgetary concerns and scope creep are very real, I think it is important to address the notion that creating a powerful archaeological data research tool is somehow at odds with building a great system for managing cultural resources on a more administrative level. When archaeologists (whether commercial or academic) search for information in our inventory of 45,000 sites, they're expecting data that's to some degree comprehensive. Unfortunately, data from some of the most important sites in the Commonwealth investigated outside of any regulatory processes have often fallen through the cracks. Hundreds of theses, dissertations, and academic publications have no doubt created typologies and identified patterns that have not made their ways back to DHR's inventory. And this all has a recursive impact on CRM and agency decision-making. How can we effectively understand a site's significance or rarity if its connections remain unrecorded (or under-recorded)? Research and management are interconnected. Respecting both priorities will elevate the discipline as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Open data and interoperability&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to facilitating good research within and beyond our agency, we need to use our data for outreach in many different ways, and it's not always easy. Archaeological data come with a caveat: locational information and details about the specific nature of certain sites may be very sensitive and protected  under state or Federal law. In the past, many SHPOs, including mine, have taken a relatively conservative approach to releasing any data to the public. But not all data are sensitive. By consciously arranging our archaeological data in a way that allows us to protect what's vulnerable and release what's not, we can build flexible new tools for outreach, planning, management, and research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A Hexagon map of cultural resource priority areas" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Smith_5.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2013, our archaeological data has been a part of the Digital Index of North American Archaeology. Having our data available at a safely publishable scale has been exceptionally fruitful for outreach and interpretation. Since DINAA has already done the work of representing the data in interoperable ways, we've been able to use it again ourselves  for multiple purposes through the SHPO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="DINAA screenshots" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Smith_6.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few weeks ago, a researcher inquired about obscured locations to use for a public map showing burial mounds in Virginia. In a matter of minutes, I was able to pull a DINAA query and create a quick interactive GeoJSON map to answer this research question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mound map for a researcher" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Smith_7.JPG"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://opencontext.org/subjects-search/?q=mound&amp;amp;proj=52-digital-index-of-north-american-archaeology-dinaa---52-virginia-site-files&amp;amp;prop=54-time-period---54-woodland-1200-bc-1606-ad%7C%7C54-late-woodland-1000-1606%7C%7C54-middle-woodland-300-999-ad%7C%7C54-early-woodland-1200-bc-299-ad%7C%7C54-earlymiddle-woodland-1200-bc-999-ad#8/37.783/-80.855/11/any/Google-Satellite"&gt;See the mound query results for yourself.&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with the DINAA team, I developed a proof of concept interactive map for disaster response using the same data. This mobile map, or a tool like it, could connect emergency responders to SHPO staff quickly and efficiently (Smith et al. 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/aejolene/disastermap"&gt;View the full paper and try the interactive map.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aejolene/disastermap/master/Slide10.JPG&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, our DINAA data is getting stale. It's from 2013. What's stopping us from building our own API at both a protected and a public scale? We could serve live data straight to DINAA and also use it to create views of data to meet agency outreach and planning needs. Why send all users with varying degrees of experience to a rich-but-confusing VCRIS map viewer when we can tailor data views to answer questions? This approach could streamline agency reviews and help everyone make better decisions. By laying the foundations with documented, controlled vocabularies and making our data available through APIs, we could set ourselves up to connect to repositories like tDAR and other institutional and online repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By opening up this way, I argue we could do &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; to keep sensitive information safe, as static GIS data and file distribution would continue to decrease. We could reduce duplication of our own effort by eliminating silos. And we could facilitate archaeology outreach in ways that have been impossible before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work will never be done. There will always be material to digitize,  files to describe and arrange, data to clean. It’s easy to get frustrated at loose ends and messiness, at red tape and slow bureaucratic timelines. But if we check our perfectionism at the door and strive toward goals of openness and interoperability with the resources we've got, we can tap into something much bigger, a little bit at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; These aren't all records for buildings, but generally about the above-ground world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Council of Virginia Archaeologists. 2009. “Howard MacCord Resolution.” &lt;a href="http://cova-inc.org/News/2009/maccordResolution.PDF"&gt;http://cova-inc.org/News/2009/maccordResolution.PDF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Library of Virginia. 2004. “A Guide to the Department of Conservation and Development, Division of History, Records, 1927-1950 Conservation and Development, Department of, Division of History 24806a-c , 25913 and 41571.” 2004. &lt;a href="http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00960.xml;query="&gt;http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=lva/vi00960.xml;query=&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miller, Diane. 1994. “National Register Information Is a Hidden Treasure.” CRM 17, no. 2, page 13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, Jolene. 2016. “Approaches to Openness.” Society for Historical Archaeology, Baltimore, MD. &lt;a href="https://jolenesmith.net/approaches-to-openness/html"&gt;https://jolenesmith.net/approaches-to-openness/html.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, Jolene, David G. Anderson, Eric Kansa, Joshua Wells, and Stephen Yerka. 2017. “Using the Digital Index of North American Archaeology for Rapid Disaster Response and Reporting.” Keeping History Above Water, Annapolis, MD. &lt;a href="https://github.com/aejolene/disastermap"&gt;https://github.com/aejolene/disastermap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data"></category><category term="inventory"></category></entry><entry><title>10 years, 3 Supervisors, 7 assistants and 30 students. How the Iowa Office of the State Archaeologist managed, manages and plans for the future of archaeological data</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/ia-delagarza.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Mary De La Garza</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-04-05:/SAA2018digigovt/ia-delagarza.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;Mary De La Garza&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainable accessible data storage is as important to archaeologists as tractors are to farmers. In 2001, the University of Iowa Office of the State Archaeologist (OSA) was archiving 20GB of data on a 100GB server and recognized that the addition of a staff member to focus …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;Mary De La Garza&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainable accessible data storage is as important to archaeologists as tractors are to farmers. In 2001, the University of Iowa Office of the State Archaeologist (OSA) was archiving 20GB of data on a 100GB server and recognized that the addition of a staff member to focus on network, database, server, and related digital issues was of paramount importance. Seventeen years later, as OSA’s Director of Research Technology, I manage how the office serves 32TB of data via several server systems. I am planning to archive up to 60TB over the next four years. In addition to digital space management, the office must also make portions of these data in its many forms accessible to outside entities, involving us in significant technical data security issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the not so distant past, archaeologists had only one archival option, securing and storing paper, photos, and film in Hollinger boxes stacked to the ceilings, sometimes but not always in dedicated Archives spaces. These days, many archaeological agencies have scanned and archived massive amounts of data to server systems taking up less space and containing many times more data. The OSA has taken advantage of several grants to scan and archive over 400,000 sheets of paper and 58,853 photos and slides, and also to digitize as GIS shapefiles the locations of nearly 30,000 archaeological sites. The advantages of digitization include preservation, accessibility (including control over access to sensitive data), and scalability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Preservation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A near-miss experience with a tornado in 2006 galvanized OSA’s efforts to digitize our paper documents and photographs. Although this was the first-ever tornado to touch down within the Iowa City limits and such an event has happily not been repeated since, the threat was all too apparent. The archived associated records now held by the OSA are 93 percent digital with original paper preservation copies also available for reference if needed. The paper record is protected to our best ability, but realistically remains vulnerable to tornadoes, floods, and fire. The digital record is better protected through storage on servers at multiple locations, but it is part of the electronic infrastructure our society as a whole is increasingly dependent upon. In our view, keeping original paper records is an important complementary aspect of creating the digital counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, OSA staff struggled with the classic problem of an Archive with just one paper copy of in-demand documents—who had it at any given time? A paper-based check-out system was used (by some) but there was always a hunt in progress! Digitization has greatly relieved this problem with most of the staff now only accessing digital versions of one-of-a-kind records via their desktops (and increasingly, through their mobile devices). This means of course that multiple users can access the same document, and there is no fear of a document or photograph being misplaced. Likewise, for researchers and companies who conduct archaeological consulting, it is no longer necessary to drive to Iowa City to access data. By logging into our interface, I-SitesPro or I-SitesPro GIS, qualified and licensed users can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;View shape files in a browser or through a mobile application,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create and export markup on locations of interest,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;query our databases,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;check out site numbers and submit new or supplemental site data,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;read project reports,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access the Collections database, and    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access site data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to these data on a 24/7/365 basis has greatly increased the general efficiency of the consulting work being conducted. Digital access also has the potential to increase the quality and sophistication of consulting as it opens up access to comparative data, literature, and images otherwise difficult for remote researchers to discover and utilize. While these resources are available to researchers visiting the OSA facility, most project budgets typically limit such visits, and there is rarely time allotted for follow-up. Digital access allows researchers to return to the OSA Archives at will to pursue unfolding research questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sensitive Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping sensitive data secure comes with challenges. We no longer rely on a lock on the door and an archivist checking you in or out of a secure area. If you are planning on hosting your data, consider the following so that you can avoid catastrophic theft and vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware and software firewalls are necessary.    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign user passwords with random password generators, and they are strong.    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not allow users to change their passwords without using your password generator.    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review your user list on a regular basis.    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patch your servers as prescribed.    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your virus software is up to date.    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand where your data resides, who manages it, and stay in touch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, photographic data can be as telling as shape files. Time must be taken to ensure photos that can potentially give away site information are treated as such. They should be tagged and secured accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Scalability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big data is here to stay and archaeological opportunities to make use of it are at our discipline’s doorstep. As noted, OSA grew from using and archiving 20GB of data to using 32TB in just 16 years. Digital usage is only going to grow at an even faster rate. It is really not hard to imagine once you factor in not only scanned paper files, but also photos, video, SQL DBs, orthomosaic, DSM, point cloud, mesh (.obj .mtl . jpg), LiDAR, and LAS files generated by an increasingly high-resolution array of digital devices. One example I’m involved with is use of unmanned aerial vehicle (a.k.a., drones) in archaeology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The drone" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/delagarza_1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is ArchE1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With ArchE1, I flew two flights over 13LA12 (Gast Farm), an expansive Middle and Late Woodland village site located in southeast Iowa, on May 7 and August 25, 2017. Those two flights led me to collect 30GB of photos, thermal images, video, audio, telemetry, and lots and lots of log data. I have then created from these field data another 10GB of models, and I’ve just scratched the surface of what is possible for digital analyses of this site.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="3D model of an archaeological site" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/delagarza_2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3D Gast Farm model from 400 feet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Future Plans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today our data sits on servers in an Enterprise environment that has some scalability in place. When I say some, I mean that if all of my users started to routinely dump 30-40GB projects onto the system without considering space in as short a period as I did back in the summer of 2017, a few things would have to take place that are time consuming and costly. First, a new server would have to be ready to go on-line with additional space, and data would have to be migrated. Alternatively, storage space could be added to our current random array of independent drives (RAID) in chunks, but doing so would necessarily disrupt service. Secondly, if our users start to hit our data at a greater frequency than expected, a server would have to be prepared and put up to handle the traffic and provide expected access speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving into the future, the OSA, like other big data generating and maintaining organizations, must develop and plan for digital security, storage, and accessibility in ways that protect sensitive data. Security is paramount in any organization but especially so when culturally sensitive data is in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our plan is to put our data securely in a scalable system that does not rely on a server needing to be prepared and put up in a matter of hours. So how will I accomplish this? Via two systems with scalable mirrors in two separate locations. Key characteristics of this design include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A plan for accommodating future storage capacity,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the use of SRM to calculate changing growth,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one server up while the other waits to be called,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;readily available and expandable space,    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;traffic that can be diverted and balanced between servers when traffic is high, and    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;separate locations in case of catastrophic events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage resource management (SRM) is used to analyze and manage storage in the enterprise environment. It is pricey but the results are clean and it beats trolling stacks of backup data to get an idea of how much data capacity your system will need in the future. I see it as an investment in your time because spending all those extra hours trying to figure out what you need can be as easy as running a report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is more to managing and scaling accessible sensitive data than meets the eye especially when you consider all the complexities of our archaeology world. Proceed with caution and a lot of secure server spaces.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="digitization"></category><category term="archives"></category><category term="sensitive-data"></category></entry><entry><title>Can you make me a map? Making Louisiana’s cultural resources records accessible</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/map-watson.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Rachel Watson</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-04-03:/SAA2018digigovt/map-watson.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="rwatson@crt.la.gov"&gt;Rachel Watson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October of 2004 the Louisiana Department of Culture, Recreation and Tourism, Office of Cultural Development (OCD) and the LA Department of Transportation and Development (DOTD) signed an interagency agreement to develop a comprehensive statewide cultural resources GIS system, the Louisiana Cultural Resources Map. The State Historic Preservation …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="rwatson@crt.la.gov"&gt;Rachel Watson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October of 2004 the Louisiana Department of Culture, Recreation and Tourism, Office of Cultural Development (OCD) and the LA Department of Transportation and Development (DOTD) signed an interagency agreement to develop a comprehensive statewide cultural resources GIS system, the Louisiana Cultural Resources Map. The State Historic Preservation Office is part of OCD which house the Division of Archaeology (DOA) and Division of Historic Preservation (DHP). Staff constraints prevented an in-house development, so we hired a contractor.  DOTD administered the contract. The requirements were that the firm hired would use the most current version of ArcView, ArcView SDE, and ArcView IMS to develop the system and the accompanying website and would have experience dealing with historic properties. A local Baton Rouge engineering firm, Gulf Engineers Consultants, Inc. hereafter referred to as GEC, Inc. won the contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson1" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_1.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now maintain our desktop applications and website utilizing ESRI products. We have migrated the online map to ArcGIS online. To maintain the system, in the face of uncertain budgets, we have implemented a fee. The fee, $1300 for an annual subscription, is used to purchase hardware, storage, and maintain software maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 2" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_2.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was to be completed in two Phases over the period of three years. Phase I consisted of two tasks: Task 1 - Digitization of site data, and Task 2 - Database and Web interface design and implementation. Much of Task 1 required on-site personnel and Task 2 required input and coordination with DOA, DHP, and DOTD personnel. Phase II consisted of scanning the archaeological site forms, the standing structure forms, and the cultural resources reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before digitization, a geodatabase was created with four feature classes projected in UTM NAD 83 Zone 15 Meters. This data set was developed from a previous database; known as the Louisiana Computerized Archaeological Database (LACAD), which the DOA had created to keep track of our site file information and to be able to use this information to answer specific questions. The LACAD was a great help when we began the process of developing the geo-database since we had already identified what the DOA felt were important searchable criteria. Any of these categories are searchable.
For the completion of this task, GEC housed two employees as well as the required computer hardware and software on the premises of the DOA. Through scanning digitizing directly from the DOA map collection, GEC digitized approximately 17,000 archaeological sites into the three geodatabase feature classes. A state-wide set of DRGs in NAD 83 was used as a reference in digitizing. DRG, or digital raster graphic, is raster image of a scanned USGS standard series topographic map, usually including the original border information, referred to as the map collar, map surround, or marginalia. Source maps are georeferenced to the surface of the earth, fit to the universal transverse Mercator (UTM) projection, and scanned at a minimum resolution of 250 dpi. The accuracy and datum of a DRG match the accuracy and datum of the source map. As sites were digitized, the trinomial site number was entered as a unique identifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approximately 54,000 historic standing structure sites were digitized into point features. Historic Districts were saved as polygon features. For those structures with inadequate maps, their location was captured through a combination of scanning maps and digitizing from records, similar to the process for Archaeological sites. DHP had begun work on a database containing information regarding their standing structure information. For structures with existing database records, geocoding will be accomplished by importing existing databases into a tabular format (.dbf) compliant with the geocoding criteria. These steps include parsing the address, standardizing abbreviated values, assigning each address element to a category known as a match key, indexing the needed categories, searching the reference data, assigning a score to each potential candidate, filtering the list of candidates based on the minimum match score, and delivering the best match. The locations represented in the formatted tables were processed through the use of EZLocate geocoding software. Geocoded sites were checked for accuracy against the USGS and non-USGS maps and corrected as needed. Records that are not able to be geocoded required slight manipulation (e.g., modifying highway names/numbers, spellings). Sites that cannot be geocoded will be researched and digitized directly into the system. After all the sites are entered in digital format either by hand or through geocoding, the standing structure resource number will be entered as a unique identifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An inventory of any new archaeological sites and historic standing structures registered with DOA and DHP during the digitizing process will be conducted at the completion of the digitization process.  These new sites will be checked and digitized in the final week of Task 1. This will ensure an up-to-date geodatabase. DHP and DOA personnel will be trained in data entry so that future updates can be conducted in-house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was planned that the geodatabases would undergo quality assurance/ quality control or (QA/QC) procedures on a weekly basis to determine accuracy and to accurately report progress. Progress reports were to be delivered to DOTD, DOA, and DHP on a biweekly basis. However, when Hurricane Katrina and Rita struck the Gulf coast in 2005 this procedure was not followed for a reason explained later in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With input from DOA and DHP, GEC attributed the feature classes of the geodatabase with relevant data from the site forms and standing structure forms. A hyperlink field was created in each feature class to attach scanned documents while completing document conversion or Phase II. Metadata is being completed for each feature class. Metadata is the information that describes the content, quality, condition, origin, and other characteristics of data or other pieces of information. Metadata for spatial data may describe and document its subject matter; how, when, where, and by whom the data was collected; availability and distribution information; its projection, scale, resolution, and accuracy; and its reliability with regard to some standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GEC used ArcIMS and .Net technology to create a secure web interface housed at the (DCRT).  Queries were developed on categories specified by DOA and DHP. The Web site displays the cultural resources data over DRG Quad maps. Additionally, site numbers are displayed as the cursor passes over a site (similar to a “tool tip”); clicking on a site while its layer is active will display the site data; and clicking on the hyperlink field in a site’s data will access a scan of the original site forms or historic standing structure documents – as they become and available. We have since migrated the website to an ArcGIS online platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GEC scanned approximately 108,000 pages of standing structure forms, photos, and documents for DHP and 668,000 pages of reports and site forms for DOA as the remaining money permits. Working with CRT personnel, GEC will develop an indexing system to enable easy filing and retrieval of scanned documents. All scanned documents will then be indexed accordingly and entered into the appropriate hyperlink field created in Phase I, Task 2, Database Design and Web Interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 4" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_4.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two separate websites; the structures and historic district data, and the archaeological site and survey reports are in a password-protected website. The legend and layers list, print, and query (still being developed) function are in the title banner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 5" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_5.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The search bar defaults to the address locator. However, the user can search for all the following categories; archaeological sites, reports, cities, and public survey lines. Search categories within archaeological includes; site number, name, parish, site components, characteristics, affiliation, function, material, and feature type. These characteristics were defined on our LACAD form available on the department website. Searchable categories for survey reports include; report number, title, author, and date. All the associated paper records are hyperlinked in a .pdf format. Multiple records can be associated with a single geographic location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 6" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_6.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 7" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_7.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 8" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_8.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional widgets on the site include the base map, add data, select tool, draw, and coordinate conversions. The base map widget allows the user to change the map view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 9" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_4.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The add data widget allows the user to upload a shapefile or kmz/kml. Furthermore, the add data widget give the user access to from ESRI AcrGIS Online content or a URL for another GIS service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 10" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_10.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The select tool allows the user to select records within a geographic region. The draw tool is useful for measuring distances and drawing buffers around features.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 11" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_11.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the coordinate conversion tool lets the user enter a coordinate in latitude/longitude or UTM. The site contains a coordinate bar that tracks the geographic location of the mouse. The coordinate bar will default to show the latitude and longitude. You can place a point to get the UTM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 12" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_12.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we had to change our strategy after the hurricanes, we launched the website before the geodatabases were complete. When we launched the website, GEC was still in the process of doing the data entry. Some sites had little more than geographical information in the database. Also, the task of scanning and hyperlinking the sites &amp;amp; standing structure forms was not complete. This required researcher to continue to visit the office until we completed the data entry.
 
We did have problems that were not a result of the storms. Much of the information from the LACAD database was in code. We had to convert the code. Since you can select for numerous entries under the categories designated for the LACAD sheet, this means there has to be more than one field in the database. We migrated the data from Microsoft Access to SQL. Migrating the website to ArcGIS online solved the data query issues.
 
Another problem that we found in working with the archaeological data was the lack of information provided on site forms. Some of our site forms consist of little more than a circle on a map if we are lucky. In some instances, there are reports of a site somewhere within a Section, Township, and Range. In these cases, we included the record in the geodatabase, but they do not display on the online map.
 
We discovered that because we did not use a placeholder in our trinomial site identification number, it made indexing the scanned pdfs difficult. We had to re-index the geodatabase placeholder for the archaeological site forms to make the hyperlinks work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 13" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_13.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as we launched the website, many entities contacted us about obtaining the actual layer data; this posed an interesting problem for us. Although, the standing structure information is public, both State and Federal law protect the archaeological information. There are several things that we needed to consider. One, how do we protect this information once we have released it? Two, how often do we offer updates on this information? And three, do we charge a fee for the release of the information? We feel that data-share agreements will solve this problem. However, these agreements take time.
 
We did implement an annual fee of $1300 in 2017. The fee has allowed us to self-generate funds to pay for GIS software license renewals to maintain the system at the time of ever shirking budgets.  Furthermore, we have used the money to continue training for the GIS staff to help maintain the system. We currently have twenty-six subscribers. Subscribers include federal agencies, state agencies, and CRM firms. Researchers and Native American tribes have free access to the system. Free access requires a research statement to document the use of the system falls within the fee exemption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 14" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_14.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the access to the archaeological site information is restricted. We are planning to create maps that the general public can view without site-specific information. As part of other programmatic agreements as a result of Section 106 projects associated with hurricane recovery, archaeological probability maps are being created for New Orleans. We are hoping to incorporate these maps into our system as a management tool.
DOA and DOTD developed a driving trail to highlight thirty-nine mounds in Northeast Louisiana. The format is in a brochure form. We plan to convert the brochure into a driving story map formatted for tablets and phones. Furthermore, we plan to develop a story map of archaeological sites on public lands.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we are working to update the report and data submission standards to aid in maintaining an up to date system. Submission standards will include new media requirement and online site form submissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Watson slide 15" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Watson_15.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a comprehensive GIS system can be a daunting task. However, we spent many hours in planning sessions to come up with what we felt is the best and most efficient way to implement this project. However, you know what they say about the best-laid plans. The partnering between state agencies to create a comprehensive system was very successful. Exploring partnership opportunities can be of great help to agencies with budget constraints.
Most of our responses to the system have been positive. CRM firms, State and Federal Agencies, and individuals with GIS experience have found the system easy to use. We believe we have developed a powerful tool to make well-informed decisions concerning cultural resource management.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="gis"></category><category term="sensitive-data"></category></entry><entry><title>The Maryland Archaeological Synthesis Project: One State’s Solution to Archaeology’s Crushing Gray Literature Problem</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/synthesis-mcknight.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matthew McKnight</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-03-16:/SAA2018digigovt/synthesis-mcknight.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="matthew.mcknight@maryland.gov"&gt;Matthew McKnight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mht.maryland.gov/secure/synthesis/"&gt;Maryland Archaeological Synthesis Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since passage of the National Historic Preservation Act fifty-three
years ago a growing body of valuable data has been generated by state
agencies, CRM professionals, and preservation officers. Unfortunately,
this data is usually trapped in an archaic paper-based format,
restricted geographically to a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="matthew.mcknight@maryland.gov"&gt;Matthew McKnight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mht.maryland.gov/secure/synthesis/"&gt;Maryland Archaeological Synthesis Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since passage of the National Historic Preservation Act fifty-three
years ago a growing body of valuable data has been generated by state
agencies, CRM professionals, and preservation officers. Unfortunately,
this data is usually trapped in an archaic paper-based format,
restricted geographically to a single state archive. All too often the
data is brought to light only to be “reburied” in the SHPO’s library
where it may be largely inaccessible to researchers scattered throughout
the country. This paper describes how the Maryland Historical Trust is
addressing this problem through the establishment of a secure, online,
searchable catalog of raw data and CRM reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defining “Gray Literature”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within Archaeology, a substantial body of print data exists in a form
typically classified by the library science community as “fugitive”
literature or more commonly by archaeologists as “gray” literature. A
considerable amount of time and attention has been dedicated to defining
what gray literature is, its strengths and weaknesses, and methods of
providing access to it (Warnick 2001, Denda 2002, Seely 2005, Stock and
Schöpfel 2003, Owen 1997, Harrison 2005, Schöpfel 2006). While the
defining characteristics of gray literature and the motives for creating
it are debated within the library community, the key factor that sets it
apart from traditional monographs or serial publications is the mode(s)
of distribution used. Alberani and De Castro (2001: 237) define gray
literature as, “material that is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; circulated through the usual
commercial channels, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; easily found, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; always available, etc.”.
Commercial publishers are not involved in the dissemination of gray
literature. Any form of profit typically takes a back seat in the effort
to distribute the material and, thus, access to such literature can be
difficult or nearly impossible. At any rate, access does not come
through the “normal” avenues of bookseller, journal subscription, or
library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research librarians have pointed out that obtaining comprehensive
information on specific archaeological sites is a particularly
challenging issue for them, in large part because of the proliferation
of gray literature within our field (Seely 2005: 2, Adelman and Markson
1987). If this is a problem for research librarians, then surely it is a
problem for the community of archaeologists. Dr. Dean Snow, former
President of the Society for American Archaeology lamented as recently
as 2010 that despite the proliferation of a number of useful online
tools providing access to archaeological data in recent years, vast
troves of unpublished CRM reports remain inaccessible or very difficult
to access (2010: 350).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, this state of affairs has been exacerbated by the
growth in research driven by compliance with the National Historic
Preservation Act of 1966 (Snow, et al. 2006, Lattanzi 1999, Childs and
Corcoran 2000) and similar state laws, and now even local ordinances in
some areas. Publically-funded archaeology has also produced a similar
proliferation of gray literature in other parts of the world (Adelman
and Markson 1987, Cohen, Murowchick and Kao 2018). Unfortunately, this
data is often restricted geographically to one or a few government
archives in a given state. In the United States, the State Historic
Preservation Office (SHPO) that reviews CRM work usually becomes the
final repository for compliance-driven archaeological reports. Any given
SHPO’s library is often inaccessible to researchers scattered throughout
the country, resulting in the effective “reburial” of archaeological
data that has only recently come to light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another factor in the proliferation of gray literature is a dramatic
expansion in the scope of the data that archaeologists recover.
Innovation in data recovery and analysis methods have made the recovery
of ethnobotanical remains, animal bone, debitage, sherdlets, and other
materials a part of routine recovery, while archaeologists of an earlier
era would have discarded or overlooked these materials. As a
consequence, “[t]he level of documentation now demanded by our
discipline impedes the function of the publication process as a tool to
preserve the archaeological record” (Kansa 2005: 98). The result is that
less and less data is being disseminated through traditional publication
channels and more is being consigned to gray literature or is not
circulated at all. This adds to the sheer volume of gray literature and
with no ready method by which to cull through it in pursuit of a
particular research topic, synthesis and data integration become next to
impossible (Kansa 2005: 98, Snow 2010: 352).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gray Literature and Archaeological Synthesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explosive growth of gray literature, particularly compliance-driven
research reports, creates some serious problems for regional
archaeological synthesis and study of specific research questions.
Synthesis of archaeological research is built upon past experience. But
what happens when a given researcher’s sphere of “past experience” is
skewed towards data that has been generated through one process (i.e.
academic or grant-funded research) at the expense of another (compliance
driven work)? The “big picture” gets warped! The only way for
archaeologists to begin drawing accurate conclusions is if data from the
past is readily available from both “pure research” and “compliance”
perspectives (Bradley 2006). In addition, data generated as a result of
compliance-driven research is publically-funded. This data was largely
collected at the public’s expense, but if it is not incorporated into
syntheses of archaeological research, it remains inaccessible to the
public (Snow 2010: 352, Lawrence, et al. 2014: 3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1998, a survey was conducted by the Council for British Archaeology
in which both archaeologists and lay readers were questioned about why
archaeological project publications and archives were being
under-utilized in the British Isles. The results of that survey
pinpointed the boom in archaeological gray literature as one of the most
pressing issues. There, as in the United States, this “boom” has been
largely generated by CRM research (what is called “developer-funded”
research in Britain). The survey revealed that many researchers simply
did not consult such literature and, “that those others who might wish
to use it are often not doing so, chiefly because of their unawareness
of its existence or difficulties of access” (Jones, et al. 2001: 6.2.2).
This survey was conducted during a period of explosive growth in
Internet technologies and the potential that these new technologies held
for solving the problem of access did not go unnoticed in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conjunction with the survey, a consortium composed of the Council for
British Archaeology, several British universities, and other agencies
began working to provide online access to archaeological gray literature
through the Archaeology Data Service portal (ADS 2018). This valuable
resource provides free access to summary site reports that have been
uploaded by participating CRM professionals, academics, and governmental
agencies. In addition, data archives, scanned library resources, and
even online data analysis tools are made available free to the public -
all searchable via web-based applications. Millions of archaeological
site and monument records from throughout the British Isles have been
uploaded into the ADS databases and the service’s &lt;em&gt;ADS Library&lt;/em&gt; includes
links to nearly 300,000 bibliographic records, including scanned site
reports (ADS 2018). While the Archaeology Data Service does not offer
complete coverage (participation is voluntary), it is a far more
comprehensive effort than has been implemented in the United States. The
influential British prehistorian, Richard Bradley, criticized the apathy
of many of his colleagues towards developer-funded (i.e. CRM) research,
stating that any synthesis of archaeological knowledge which ignores
such gray literature is bound to be erroneous (Bradley 2006). If
syntheses of British archaeology can be faulted, with ready availability
of CRM reports through the Archaeology Data Service, how much more
questionable must synthesis research in the United States be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, it is not as if this problem is being ignored by American
archaeologists. Increasing numbers of researchers in the United States
are exploring the potential of Internet technologies to provide access
to archives of digital archaeological data. One can look back as early
as the 1980s, when National Park Service personnel began advocating for
the creation of a centralized database of bibliographic references for
archaeological work throughout the country. The National Archaeological
Database (NADB) was a compilation of over 350,000 bibliographic
references for research reports and analyses, a majority of which could
be classified as gray literature (CAST and NPS 2015).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evolution of the Internet brought with it increasing calls for the
online publication of similar bibliographic reference lists, and also
the documents themselves. A growing number of publications and
conference presentations have begun to focus on issues of
“cyberinfrastructure” in archaeology (Kansa 2005, Snow, et al. 2006,
Kintigh 2006a, Kintigh 2006b, Snow 2010, Rivers Cofield and Reeves
Flores 2014, Kintigh et al. 2014). Many of these authors specifically
note the inadequacy of synthesis which does not take into account
“unpublished” data forms. They argue that the creation of
cyberinfrastructure would simultaneously preserve data and provide wider
access which would aide synthesis and lead to more accurate
archaeological interpretations in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And American archaeologists are putting their money (or at least their
creative energies) where their mouth is. The Archaeology Data Service in
Britain has already been mentioned, but in the mid-2000s, the ADS began
working with the Center for Advanced Spatial Technologies and a
consortium of universities, not-for-profit research institutes, and CRM
professionals calling itself “Digital Antiquity” (formerly
Archaeoinformatics.org) to produce an international cyberinfrastructure
for archaeology (Digital Antiquity 2018). This consortium has developed
software prototypes and infrastructures for preserving and providing
access to digital archaeological data such as text, images, GIS,
research databases, and the like. The tangible outgrowth of their work
has been the tDAR (the Digital Archaeological Record) database, which at
last check included over 390,000 document records (Brin 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of smaller-scale efforts are also underway, focusing on more
restricted geographic areas or particular topics of interest. Boston
University’s International Center for East Asian Archaeology and
Cultural History, working with a broad consortium of Asian universities,
research institutes, museums, and cultural heritage agencies has been
building a database of bibliographic records for both published and
unpublished works of archaeological interest (Cohen, Murowchick and Kao
2018). A significant proportion of the records being incorporated into
the so-called “ARC/Base” database are government mandated site reports.
The quantity of such reports in East Asia is expected to grow rapidly in
the next few decades as new laws in China, Korea, and other Asian
countries begin to drive excavation in the same way North American
cultural resource management laws have driven research here (Cohen,
Murowchick and Kao 2018). Another example is the Museum of Underwater
Archaeology’s (MUA) Gray Literature Bibliographic Database. The MUA
project includes bibliographic references for Phase I and II submerged
resources reports, as well as redacted copies of the reports in some
instances. This database currently includes references for 296 reports
from 5 Atlantic seaboard states and a few federal agencies, but is
working to incorporate data from more states (MUA 2018). There are
numerous other examples scattered across the web of similar projects
focusing on particular subsets of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, a number of State Historic Preservation Offices have
taken steps to begin making state-curated archaeological data available
over the internet. A recent review of SHPO websites undertaken by the
author revealed that 24 states currently offer online access to some or
all of their site file data. Several others report that they are
currently working towards that goal. But of these 24 states, only half
(AR, DE, GA, IL, LA, MD, NM, NY, OR, PA, WA, and WY) appear to offer
some level of access to CRM site report data via the internet. Most of
these states provide access to either 1) a subset of the gray literature
reports available in the SHPO’s physical library, or 2) search
functionality for scanned CRM report abstracts or summary reports. Most
of the states either offer the archaeological data through a
password-protected website accessible only to professional
archaeologists, or through a paywall which helps to cover the costs of
maintaining the data. One state, Delaware, has scanned all of the gray
literature reports related to Department of Transportation projects and
made them freely available to the public, but the reports have been
heavily redacted to protect site location data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obstacles to Online Gray Literature&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we see more widespread access to CRM gray literature data online,
a number of obstacles need to be overcome. First and foremost among
these is the now archaic format in which most of the gray literature
data has been collected: paper-based reports. While many SHPOs now
accept or even require the submission of CRM reports digitally for
review and compliance purposes, every state has a significant backlog of
print reports in their libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a geographically quite small state such as Maryland, the CRM backlog
consisted of approximately 3,700 reports just a few years ago. This
represents many hundreds of thousands of printed pages of data. With
such sheer volume at the outset, it can be daunting to contemplate how
to even begin addressing the problem. Though it is tempting to think
that improvements in the efficiencies and costs of scanning technologies
and optical character recognition software should allay concerns with
volume, state budgets typically prioritize existing programs over new
initiatives. On one level, it may be more practical and cost-effective
to build searchable databases that cover only the incoming gray
literature while ignoring the print backlog. However, it is not
sufficient. In order for true archaeological synthesis to take place,
databases need to be comprehensive and cover both print and
digitally-submitted reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major obstacle is the SHPOs’ responsibility to protect site
location data. Government employees are obligated under several pieces
of federal and, in many cases, state legislation to protect site
location data (Carnett 1991: 6-7). Obviously, this limits the ways in
which CRM report data can be provided to the public. However, as others
have noted (Snow 2010: 352), this data was collected at significant
public expense and there is also an ethical obligation to make the gray
literature data available to the public on at least some level. SHPOs
often find themselves caught in a tug-of-war between these two disparate
obligations. Again, this can lead to an unwillingness to tackle the
problem, or at the very least, uncertainty about how to go about doing
so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the sheer volume of data contained in a typical CRM gray
literature report can be an obstacle in and of itself. In Maryland,
cultural resource management reports can routinely run upwards of 300
pages in length. Compare this to the typical gray literature report
available through the British Archaeological Data Service: while reports
sometimes do approach 300 pages in length, the vast majority appear to
be 30 or fewer pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this disparity are the subject of an entirely different
paper, but the bulk of CRM reports in the US can actually be an
impediment to research. Investigators tend to have a fairly narrow topic
of interest in mind. Even if a given researcher is able to locate a
report of potential interest, the manuscript may be so large that it is
not easily digestible. Having read thousands of these reports, I suggest
that perhaps brevity is not valued highly enough in American
archaeology. It can be quite difficult to get a “feel” for a site when
so much of the really valuable data is being drowned out by “noise”.
Furthermore, locating the data of interest can be a
needle-in-the-haystack exercise when reports are so large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solving the Gray Literature Problem(s)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2007, the Maryland Historical Trust (MHT), the SHPO for the State of
Maryland, embarked upon an ambitious project aimed at synthesizing the
now 53 years of compliance-driven archaeological research conducted
within the state since inception of the National Historic Preservation
Act. Startup work was funded by a grant from the MHT Board of Trustees,
with additional funds coming later via Transportation Enhancement funds
administered by the Maryland State Highway Administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major component of the Maryland Archaeological Synthesis Project has
been the generation of a searchable database of synopsis reports (think
expanded abstract). Additional products will eventually be overview
print and other media publications aimed toward the general public. The
development of the project database has been focused on providing both
the general public and the archaeological community with access to
Maryland’s archaeological gray literature data, while simultaneously
overcoming the three aforementioned obstacles: the paper backlog, report
volume, and site location data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned previously, the paper backlog of gray literature reports
prior to the outset of the project consisted of some 3,700 gray
literature reports for both terrestrial and maritime archaeology
undertakings. Early on it was determined that online access to all of
these reports was not feasible, nor was it necessary. A majority of
these reports are Phase I survey and reconnaissance reports. While
clearly valuable data are present, most of the really critical data is
replicated in the Maryland Archaeological Site Survey Files that CRM
contractors complete when their reports are submitted to the state for
legal review and compliance. Sites that had only been subjected to Phase
I work were already well represented in MHT’s site files and a separate
project was underway to make the site files available to professional
archaeologists online (now live). For the Synthesis Project, effort
would instead be focused on sites which had been subject to Phase II
testing and Phase III data recovery efforts. The much more comprehensive
site data in these reports is not replicated in the MHT site files and
is also the data that is likely to be of the greatest interest to both
academic researchers and the general public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While access to full site reports is desirable for certain purposes (and
MHT is working to make that possible), in the interest of data synthesis
it is often more useful to start with something smaller. Again, the size
of these reports can actually function as a hindrance to conducting
research. A researcher interested in any given topic is likely to have
dozens of print reports (each hundreds of pages long) to cull through,
before winnowing down to the handful of reports in which he or she may
actually be interested. While abstracts are helpful, they often do not
contain enough data to identify whether or not a particular site report
is worth examining further. The MHT’s synthesis project seeks to attain
a middle ground by generating “synopsis reports” or capsule summaries
that provide a snapshot of the most relevant data (see Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical synopsis report distills the most relevant data into a
manageable, digestible and typically 3-6 page format. The synopsis
reports currently in the MHT synthesis database provide an overview of
all work conducted at the site (pulled from the original print reports
by MHT staff), location and environmental information, and aggregate
data tables of site features and artifacts organized in such a way that
researchers can quickly pull out the information most relevant for their
projects. Data is also pulled directly from the MHT archaeological site
survey files to provide more detailed reports. This strategy not only
migrates the gray literature data from a paper-based format, but also
makes it more digestible. Once the researcher knows which sites are of
definite interest, they can then make arrangements to access the full
CRM report in the MHT library, and (we hope) eventually online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, site locations are protected within the Archaeological
Synthesis database by providing tiered access to these synopsis reports.
Two versions of the database have been made available online: a
password-protected version for archaeologists that meet the Secretary of
the Interior’s Professional Qualifications for Archaeologists, and an
open-access version for the general public. The data available in both
versions are identical with the exception of three fields: &lt;em&gt;Site
Setting&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Latitude&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Longitude&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Site Setting&lt;/em&gt; for professionals
typically provides a brief description of the local environment and
often detailed instructions on how to locate the site. &lt;em&gt;Latitude&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;Longitude&lt;/em&gt; represent the centroid of the site area polygon from our
in-house Geographic Information System. On the public side of the
database, &lt;em&gt;Latitude&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Longitude&lt;/em&gt; are randomized to within one square
mile of the actual site location and &lt;em&gt;Site Setting&lt;/em&gt; is entirely
restricted. MHT feels that this strategy provides an appropriate
compromise between protecting site location information and providing
the public with the data collected at their expense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Archaeological Synthesis Project is online at &lt;a href="https://mht.maryland.gov/secure/synthesis/"&gt;https://mht.maryland.gov/secure/synthesis/&lt;/a&gt;. The synopsis report data
is archived in SQL Server where it is keyword searchable via a web
interface. Researchers don’t have to have a particular site in mind when
performing a search, and thus, their past experience is no longer a
limitation to data synthesis. In addition, the database can be queried
by site name, trinomial number (or partial number), Maryland
Archaeological Research Unit, Soil types, and other variables (see
Figure 2). Each query points to any number of “hits”, and each hit
points to an URL for the site synopsis report in Adobe PDF format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each hit also points to an URL for a reference cover sheet which is
prepared to summarize the various projects (compliance or otherwise)
that were responsible for the generation of information on a site or a
given group of sites (e.g., highway widening, undergraduate fieldschool,
construction of a prison, real estate development, etc.). The project
cover sheet summarizes the purpose for the archaeological work
undertaken, the archaeological research questions asked, and other
useful information. It also provides an assessment by MHT as to whether
the site is likely to retain any additional research potential. An
example of a typical reference cover sheet is provided in Figure 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcomes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Archaeological Synthesis Project went live on the web on Maryland
Day (March 25^th^), 2015. Since then, the project has proven its
usefulness in responding to the periodic email and phone requests MHT
receives from library patrons with specific research topics in mind.
According to senior MHT staff, question responses which once would have
taken a week or more of library research work to answer, can now be
responded to in a matter of minutes. This is over and above the everyday
queries that our patrons can now make on their own (again, significantly
reducing the workload on MHT staff). In addition, the synthesized data
will help redirect future investigations to examine data gaps, provide
readily accessible comparative data to enable informed National Register
evaluations, and focus research questions to target important issues for
data recovery efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MHT’s Office of Preservation Services staff use the database on a daily
basis in their review of submitted projects for their impacts on
archaeological resources in accordance with both federal and state
historic preservation law (Section 106 of the National Historic
Preservation Act of 1966 and the Maryland Historical Trust Act of 1985).
Through the ability to search the database on a regional or statewide
basis and the detailed information presented in the accompanying
synopsis reports, staff are able to make informed and justifiable
decisions much more efficiently and accurately. The types of decisions
routinely made with the assistance of the Synthesis database include the
following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;determining the level of effort necessary for a given investigation
    based on results from previous studies as well as data gaps for a
    particular region, time period or site type;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;evaluating sites for National Register eligibility &amp;amp; placing them
    within an appropriate context;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;identifying relevant research questions to focus data recovery and
    produce useful results; and;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;helping to define appropriate mitigation measures (through
    traditional or creative means) to compensate for adverse effects to
    a significant site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One recent example involved a proposed project that had the potential to
impact surviving sections of an archaeological site that was originally
investigated and partially excavated over 30 years ago. The Birely
Tannery site (18FR575) was originally identified during planning for the
Carroll Creek flood control project during the 1970s and 1980s,
determined eligible for the National Register, and portions of the site
were excavated in 1990 prior to its destruction by the flood control
project. The data recovery investigations (Thomas et al. 1991) examined
numerous archaeological features and midden areas associated with
various aspects of the tannery operations during the 19th and early 20th
centuries. While portions of the site were destroyed for the flood
control project, archival information indicated that the site originally
extended beyond the boundaries of that specific project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a construction project subject to MHT review was proposed in this
area, staff queried the Synthesis Project database to quickly anchor
themselves in the archaeological “milieu” surrounding the site. It can
be difficult to quickly and efficiently get a handle on past
archaeological work at a site, on work at other sites in the region, on
sites of comparable research value and interest, and on sites in similar
environmental settings without such a tool. The MHT staff quickly
discovered that the Birely Tannery site (18FR575) constitutes the sole
tannery site in Maryland that has been professionally investigated at
the Phase II/III level and found to yield substantive and comprehensive
information regarding this important industry throughout the 19th and
into the mid 20th century. MHT staff recommended Phase I/II
archaeological investigations which revealed Site 18FR575 extended into
the impact area for the new construction. The new investigations
identified the remains of 13 tannery related features including: four
tanning pits, one waste pit, stone paving, and the remains of several
structural foundations. The site still contains buried surfaces and
features that survive beneath the various fill and disturbance actions
that have occurred on the site during the mid to late 20th century.
These newly discovered resources represent the site’s continuation into
the project area, as expected, and contain an important record of the
history, development and operations of the Birely Tannery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, MHT staff are seeing that archaeological consulting firms
are making use of the Archaeological Synthesis database to perform
background research and inform recommendations. In October of 2017, a
Phase II study was carried out at the Jones Farm (18QU1052) in Queen
Anne’s County prior to installation of a solar power generation complex
(Petyk 2017). The solar installation project was to be located on a
tract that was consistently used by tenant farmers, but owned by
absentee landlords dating back to at least the last quarter of the 18th
century. Ceramics recovered during the Phase II excavations on the farm
provided a mean ceramic date of 1802 for the site and also suggested a
relatively low economic status for the site’s occupants. The Phase II
investigation also identified the presence of an intact feature (likely
a cellar) near the center of the site, indicating that the farm retained
good integrity and might contain additional features associated with the
late 18th to early 19th-century occupation of the property. The Phase II
report notes that while, tenancy was a common practice in Queen Anne’s
County during the 18th and 19th centuries, examination of the
Archaeological Synthesis database revealed this type of site has been
largely understudied in the county and throughout the Eastern Shore of
the state. No 18th century tenant occupations in Queen Anne’s County
have been subjected to Phase II investigations, and only one other site
(in Talbot County) has been evaluated at the Phase II level. That site
was found to have been heavily impacted by modern disturbances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following MHT’s review of these findings and the results of the Phase II
background research, staff concurred that site 18QU1052 does indeed
possess good integrity and unique research potential and was therefore
eligible for inclusion in the National Register. MHT staff also
concurred with the recommendation that the site should be avoided during
construction and preserved in place, an arrangement that the solar
installation firm agreed to. The site was avoided by providing a
30-meter buffer from the site boundary and installing protective fencing
and signage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Archaeological Synthesis Project is also providing
opportunities for MHT staff in the Office of Research, Survey, and
Registration to step back and explore data gaps, research priorities,
development of predictive modeling, and other topics that they have
heretofore been unable to consider. Figures 4 and 5 are from a recent
analysis performed on the Archaeological Synthesis dataset to explore
sites with Late Archaic components that have been examined at the Phase
II or III level. In this case, a report was run to look only at the data
from one area: Dorchester County, Maryland. The report could have as
easily been run looking at a specific physiographic province, watershed,
or a different time period. The point is that the Office of Research now
has a tool in place (the Archaeological Synthesis Database) to begin
looking at patterns in the data and plan research priorities
accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gray literature has been vexing to whole generations of archaeologists
now that we are 53 years on since passage of the National Historic
Preservation Act. That legislation has focused intense time and energy
on the collection of data with less attention paid to how that data
would be made available so that it could inform decision-making and be
interpreted for the public. But innovative new technologies are
beginning to bridge the gap between traditional published data sources
and less-widely distributed archives of archaeological information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Maryland Historical Trust is at the forefront of this innovation,
working towards technologies that will permit rapid and ready access to
the archaeological information that we have at our disposal. With an eye
towards the future, we are attempting to design these technologies in
such a way that they can work seamlessly with other innovative projects
and as yet unimagined technologies. The end result will be a new era in
archaeology where the first true synthesis of all archaeological data,
both the research conducted in academia and the tremendous amount of
work completed by CRM professionals, becomes possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Works Cited&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adelman, Jean, and Eileen Markson
1987 Archaeology Resources in Libraries: Are they Accessible? &lt;em&gt;Art
Libraries Journal&lt;/em&gt; 12(4): 31-35.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alberani, Vilma, and Paola De Castro
2001 Grey Literature: from the York Seminar (UK) of 1978 to the year 2000. &lt;em&gt;INSPEL&lt;/em&gt; 35: 236-247.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeology Data Service (ADS)
2018 Background and ADS Library Statistics. Archaeology Data Service,
University of York, York, UK;http://archaeologydataservice.ac.uk/about/; and http://archaeologydataservice.ac.uk/library/admin/statistics.xhtml;.
Accessed 16 March 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bradley, Richard
2006 Bridging the Two Cultures – Commercial Archaeology and the Study of
Prehistoric Britain. &lt;em&gt;The Antiquaries Journal&lt;/em&gt; 86: 1-13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brin, Adam
2018 Looking Back at 2017, Part II: tDAR, Content, and Usage. The Center
for Digital Antiquity, Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ
;https://www.tdar.org/news/2018/01/looking-back-at-2017-
part-ii-tdar-content-and-usage/;. Accessed 15 March 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carnett, Carol
1991 &lt;em&gt;Legal Background of Archeological Resources Protection&lt;/em&gt;. National
Center for Cultural Resources - National Park Service, Technical Brief,
No. 11. Washington, DC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CAST and NPS
2015 National Archeological Database (NADB). Archeology Program -
National Park Service, Washington, DC
;http://www.nps.gov/archeology/tools/nadb.htm;. Accessed 14
December 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Childs, S. Terry, and Eileen Corcoran
2000 Managing Archeological Collections: Technical Assistance.
Archeology Program - National Park Service, Washington, DC
;http://www.nps.gov/archeology/collections/;. Accessed 14 December
2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen, David J., Robert E. Murowchick, and Jeffrey Y.T. Kao
2018 ARC/Base: A Comprehensive, Multilingual, Web-based Bibliographic
Database for East Asian Archaeology. International Center for East Asian
Archaeology and Cultural History, Boston University, Boston, MA
;http://www.bu.edu/asianarc/projects/arcbase/slideshow/;. Accessed
15 March 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denda, Kayo
2002 Fugitive Literature in the Cross Hairs: An Examination of
Bibliographic Control and Access. &lt;em&gt;Collection Management&lt;/em&gt; 27(2): 75-86.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital Antiquity
2018 About Digital Antiquity. Digital Antiquity, Arizona State
University, Tempe, AZ ;http://www.digitalantiquity.org/about/;.
Accessed 15 March 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harrison, John
2005 Grey Literature or Fugitive Report Project. &lt;em&gt;MLA Forum&lt;/em&gt; 4(1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jones, Siân, Ann MacSween, Stuart Jeffrey, Richard Morris, and Mike
Heyworth
2001 From The Ground Up: The Publication of Archaeological Projects, a
User Needs Survey. Council for British Archaeology, York, UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kansa, Eric
2005 A Community Approach to Data Integration: Authorship and building
meaningful links across diverse archaeological data sets. &lt;em&gt;Geosphere&lt;/em&gt;
1(2): 97-109.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kintigh, Keith
2006a The Promise and Challenge of Archaeological Data Integration.
&lt;em&gt;American Antiquity&lt;/em&gt; 71(3): 567 578.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kintigh, Keith
2006b The Challenge of Archaeological Data Integration. Paper presented
at the meeting of the Union Internationale des Sciences Préhistoriques,
Lisbon, Spain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kintigh, Keith, Jeffrey H. Altschul, Ann P. Kinzig, W. Frederick Limp,
William K. Michener, Jeremy A. Sabloff, Edward J. Hackett, Timothy A.
Kohler, Bertram Ludäscher, and Clifford A. Lynch
2014 Final Report of the Workshop - Cultural
Dynamics, Deep Time, and Data: Planning
Cyberinfrastructure Investments in Archaeology. Final report of a
workshop held February 7^th^ and 8^th^, 2013, National Science
Foundation, Arlington, VA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lattanzi, Gregory D
1999 Cultural Resource Management and the Internet: A Touch of "Gray".
&lt;em&gt;The SAA Bulletin&lt;/em&gt; 17(4): 30- 33.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawrence, Amanda, John Houghton, Julian Thomas, and Paul Weldon
2014 Where is the Evidence? Realizing the Value of Grey Literature for
Public Policy and Practice. Swinburne Institute for Social Research,
Melbourne, Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Museum of Underwater Archaeology (MUA)
2018 Gray Literature Bibliographic Database. The Museum of Underwater
Archaeology; http://www.themua.org/collections/items/browse?collection=10;.
Accessed 15 March 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owen, John Mackenzie
1997 The Expanding Horizon of Grey Literature. In &lt;em&gt;GL3 - Third
International Conference on Grey Literature&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 1-5&lt;em&gt;. 2005&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 194-203. Luxembourg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Petyk, Richard
2017 &lt;em&gt;Technical Report: Phase II Archaeological Testing at Site
18QU1052, Jones Farm E, Jones Farm&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Solar Project, Queen Anne’s County,
Maryland&lt;/em&gt;. GAI Consultants, Inc. Warrenton, VA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rivers Cofield, Sara, and Jodi Reeves Flores
2014 Evaluating a Cooperative Approach to the Management of Digital
Archaeological Records. Department of Defense Legacy Resource Management
Program, Project No. 13-711. Washington, DC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schöpfel, Joachim
2006 Observations on the Future of Grey Literature. &lt;em&gt;The Grey Journal&lt;/em&gt;
2(2): 67-76.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seely, Amber
2005 Digging Up Archaeological Information. &lt;em&gt;Behavioral and Social
Sciences Librarian&lt;/em&gt; 24 (1): 1-20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snow, Dean R
2010 Making Legacy Literature and Data Accesible in Archaeology. In
&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 37^th^ International Conference on Computer
Applications and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology,&lt;/em&gt; B. Frischer, J.
Webb Crawford and D. Koller, editors, pp. 350-355. Williamsburg, VA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snow, Dean R., Mark Gahegan, C. Lee Giles, Kenneth G. Hirth, George R.
Milner, Prasenjit Mitra, and James Z. Wang
2006 Cybertools and Archaeology. &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 311(5763): 958-959.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stock, C., and J. Schöpfel
2003 Grey Literature in an Open Context: From Certainty to New
Challenges. In &lt;em&gt;GL5 – Fifth International
Conference on Grey Literature&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 1-1. Amsterdam, Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas, Ronald A., Merle Dunn, Kathleen Ryan, Domenic Seguto, R. Bruce
Hoadley, Kenneth Baumgardt, and Robert F. Hoffman
1991 &lt;em&gt;Phase III Data Recovery at the Birely Tannery (18FR575), City of
Frederick, MD&lt;/em&gt;. MAAR Associates, Inc. Newark, DE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warnick, Walter
2001 Tailoring Access to the Source: Preprints, Grey Literature and
Journal Articles. &lt;em&gt;Nature – Web Debates&lt;/em&gt;. Published May 3, 2001.
;http://www.nature.com/nature/debates/e-access/Articles/
warnick.html;. Accessed 23 December 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/mcknight1.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1: Screenshots of a Typical Synopsis Report&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/mcknight2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2: Screenshot of the Searchable Web Interface&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/mcknight3.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3: Screenshot of a Typical Reference Cover Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/mcknight4.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4: Database Report – Analysis of Late Archaic Sites in Dorchester
County, MD (Page 1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/mcknight5.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 5: Database Report – Analysis of Late Archaic Sites in Dorchester
County, MD (Page 2)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="CRM"></category><category term="gray-literature"></category></entry><entry><title>Approaches, Rationales, and Challenges to Maintaining Site Inventory in the National Parks</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/approaches-gadsby.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>David Gadsby</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-03-14:/SAA2018digigovt/approaches-gadsby.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="David_Gadsby@nps.gov"&gt;David Gadsby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, the National Park Service (NPS) has worked to preserve natural and cultural resources in more than four hundred park units for future generations.  In addition, the National Historic Preservation Act (NHPA) requires all federal agencies to maintain inventories of their historic properties.  For decades …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="David_Gadsby@nps.gov"&gt;David Gadsby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, the National Park Service (NPS) has worked to preserve natural and cultural resources in more than four hundred park units for future generations.  In addition, the National Historic Preservation Act (NHPA) requires all federal agencies to maintain inventories of their historic properties.  For decades, the NPS has relied upon three inventory systems: The List of Classified Structures, the Cultural Landscapes Inventory (CLI), and the Archeological Sites Management Information System (ASMIS). These systems began decades ago as paper files and continue today as electronic databases accessed via the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inventories allow NPS to maintain and update critical information including resource type, location, condition, threats, and disturbances.  As the relevant technologies continue to develop with what seems like increasing rapidity, even these relatively modern databases are being rapidly rendered obsolete.  The NPS Cultural Resources, Science, and Partnerships directorate has begun work to modernize these systems, and to facilitate their further integration with GIS technologies and other NPS programs, and incorporate elements of the now defunct Ethnographic Resources Inventory (ERI).  This paper discusses the issues faced as NPS updates these crucial tools for a second century of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gadsby Title Slide" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide1.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m David Gadsby. I work in the Cultural Resources, Science and Partnerships Office of the National Park Service, where I coordinate our inventory database of archeological resources. We’re currently working to modernize our inventory systems that track information about historic buildings, cultural landscapes, ethnographic resources and archeological sites, and streamline them into a new online system. You’re looking at the ruins of Casa Grande National Monument. The ruins date to 1400s, protected through citizen activism and presidential proclamation, 1892, declared a national monument in 1918. This is an archeological site -- CAGR00014,  with a subsite. The site includes historic and Hohokam features (incl. a drainage ditch excavated by Jesse Fewkes during 1906 stabilization).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also more than one historic structure LCS 06607(shelter) On the national register – Designed by Olmsted Co.  and Thomas Vint, 01044 (Compound A) (Classic Hohokam, Also on NR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a cultural landscape – including the visitor center, Casa Grande itself and surrounding vegetation plan – part of a master plan from the 1930s.&lt;br&gt;
In addition to buried archaeological deposits and standing structures, there are facilities (like the walkways) and interpretive signage, not to mention natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a park resource management perspective, this is a fairly complex situation, with a large number of resources and resource values packed into a relatively small physical space. It is also repeated at different scales and in different configurations across the seven regions and 417 national park units.  Creating a resource inventory system that meets NPS’s diverse and complex needs presents a number of challenges.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide2.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This photo is of Keys Ranch, Joshua Tree National Park (JOTR) – it has one or more record in each of three systems: ASMIS, LCS CLI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NPS cultural resources inventory programs track four main types of park Resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structures -  have historic, architectural, or engineering significance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cultural Landscapes – defined as historically significant properties that show human interaction with the environment and are eligible for listing on NRHP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ethnographic Resources - Sites, structures, objects, landscapes, natural features that have traditional significance in the cultural system of a traditionally associated group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Archeological resources – known sites on NPS lands that have the potential to yield information about the human past through archaeology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individual resources can have more than one resource type, and the physical boundaries and management needs can vary considerably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, a landscape can be made up of multiple components, including resources that are also archeological sites and structures.
By the same token, all or part of a standing structure may also be an archeological site, and sites can be organized differently depending on the management needs of the park and the professional judgement of the archeologists doing the documentation work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we need a way to keep track of all this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide3.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, these resources are tracked in four legacy systems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of Classified Structures(LCS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cultural Landscapes Inventory(CLI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Archeological Sites Management Information System (ASMIS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ethnographic Resources Inventory (ERI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exception of ERI, which is largely defunct, these systems are built on aging web-accessible  sql server platforms that are very similar, but are nonetheless separate systems. The information in them is much older, with some ASMIS records dating back to the 19th century, and the LCS dating as a paper system back to 1960, and as a computer system to 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current iterations of these systems are very similar in a lot of ways, but all break separately.  Unifying into a single system is expected to achieve a number of cost savings and other efficiencies.  More importantly, it should allow cultural resource managers in parks to achieve a more coherent view of the resources that they manage.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide4.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo: Former Intermountain Jim Bradford dives the Captain Ed’s Wreck, a submerged archeological site in Biscayne National Park.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The requirements for our systems are laid out in several authorities – laws, regulations, and policy – that require NPS to manage its cultural resources.  Here’s a partial list just for archaeological  resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning with the 1916  Organic act that requires NPS to preserve resources in perpetuity for future generations, to the NHPA’s mandate to inventory historic resources and consider the effects of government decisions on them, to the AHPA’s requirement that the government preserve archeological data, we have a number of particular requirements that we need the systems to fulfill. In addition, restrictions on how those data are managed, such as those restricting the public release of certain information in NHPA section 304 and ARPA section 7 place further requirements on any new system.  Many of these statutes, like GRPA come with reporting requirements, so we need to be able to extract fairly specific kinds of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide5.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo: Square Tower House at Mesa Verde National Park&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the basic things we need to be able to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the structure of the NPS, and wide variation in the types of resources and level of staffing available to manage them mean that the requirements across the system vary a good deal. Managing what users are able to see and ensuring that appropriate staff have access to the records they need is really important, and throws a lot of complexity into the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need for certain key fields, (like location fields) to remain secret is in tension with the need to share information across disciplines, and especially with planners, facilities people, and first responders in the event of a disaster. We’ll talk about that problem in detail in another session Saturday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide6.JPG"&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BELA Good Hope Reindeer Herding Site&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clear mandates in the form of laws, regulations, and policy, as well as a recent commitment of funds from the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institutional experience
    Large user base means lots of expertise (comes with risk of losing that information)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide7.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;St Louis Arch at Gateway Arch NHP&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the usual dearth of staff, money, and time, some of the challenges specific to management of NPS operating environment are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Costs and Inefficiencies of maintaining separate legacy data systems:
- Legacy data is important, particularly as we witness increasing levels of change on the ground.
- The systems, and particularly the web applications that provide access are less important, and can hamper access and usability.
- We have three, and when they break, we have thrice the maintenance costs. When we update we do it three times.
- Old applications are more vulnerable to security threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining systems at the speed of government
- Old designs mean lots of maintenance, particularly as web standards, web browsers, and computers themselves modernize.
  - For example, woke up one morning to discover that several features of ASMIS depended on were no longer supported by Chrome, and users could no longer enter data using that browser.
- Older, static designs are harder to update and enhance. Some mistakes get fossilized in the system. E.g. string fields that shouldn’t be, lack of GIS-friendly location data, pick lists that used to be free text.
- Technology in industry moves much faster than government budget cycles. NPS plans some of its spending 1 year out, and some up to 3 years out.
- This means that in the time you’ve taken to fund an  intended purchase, the item/software/technology you’ve planned to acquire can become obsolete.
- We don’t have the budget and spending capacity or  flexibility to drive or keep up with industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining a data system that works for all users:
NPS has 417 park units across the United States and in the territories. This means wide variations in staffing, logistics and infrastructure,  data needs, internet connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some parks have large archeological staffs, but many have none.  Some regions have large service centers, while others have smaller programs. Different models = different needs, different terminology, different theoretical approaches. (and theory effects how you collect and store data.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combine that with the fact that we’re now planning to merge inventory systems into a new system.  So now you’re adding architects, landscape architects, and ethnographers, all with different levels of training, needs, priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to have meaningful data, you have to have a fairly high level of complexity, both in terms of user access and the structure of the data system.  (You can have simple, and you can meet meet the specific needs of a variety of users, but each comes at the cost of the other. )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also have to balance the expectations of users with what is achievable, and sensible. Too many moving parts means more to break, higher maintenance costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security
Two worries – inappropriate access by people using the system as  intended, and hacking breach.  Both need to be avoided, both present challenges.  First – inappropriate access by users, means thinking through and carefully testing, particularly when security change can ramify throughout the system.
Second is up to people at a higher pay grade to designate cybersecurity standards and provide appropriate infrastructure. But we’ve had to adapt legacy systems to ever more stringent requirements from Information resources people ( DOI OCIO, for instance). Doing so invariably breaks those systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hazard with both types of security is that appropriate users must have good access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide8.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mission Nuestra Señora de los Ángeles de Porciúncula de los Pecos (Pecos Church/Mission/Covento) In all three databases&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide9.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Images are samples of workflows and data entry features for the new system. Used with permission.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current project is to integrate the four legacy databases into one, and develop a web-accessed application.  Working name is CRIS or CRIS-P
We are currently in the throes of first year, half million dollar contract. I’d hoped to have something to demo, but it isn’t available yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasks:
- Contractor designs new database, GUI, reports and utilities.
- Migrating data from legacy databases to new
- Updating problem fields and pick lists&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the future:
- Additional reports
- Crosswalk to other databases
- GIS integration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide10.JPG"&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CAGR again&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we’re done with this first year, we’ll have a stable system that works in the field, but that will still need improvement. We’ll continue to improve into the out years so that we’re meeting user needs as best we can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide11.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2016 Archaeoblitz @ KNRI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the most basic needs – fulfilling statutory requirements, creating accurate records, saving money on system maintenance, we expect some other benefits to arise from the unified approach to inventory data.
- Particularly park managers will be able to able to see /report on at least some information about all of their park’s cultural resources in a single system.
- Data collection in the field on any devise
- Record and preserve institutional knowledge
- Long-term projects with ever-deeper time depth.
    E.g. Cochran et al ( in prep) on climate change (http://www.georgewright.org/1706cochran.pdf)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide12.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/blog/Presentations/Gadsby_Slide13.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data"></category><category term="inventory"></category></entry><entry><title>Ethics and Best Practices for Mapping Archaeological Sites</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/mapping-smith-abstract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Cecilia Smith</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-02-19:/SAA2018digigovt/mapping-smith-abstract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="cecilia1183@gmail.com"&gt;Cecilia Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principle 6 of the Society of American Archaeology’s Principles of Archaeological Ethics emphasizes archaeologists’ responsibility to publically report archaeological investigations with the stipulation that “An interest in preserving and protecting in situ archaeological sites must be taken in to account when publishing and distributing information about their …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="cecilia1183@gmail.com"&gt;Cecilia Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Principle 6 of the Society of American Archaeology’s Principles of Archaeological Ethics emphasizes archaeologists’ responsibility to publically report archaeological investigations with the stipulation that “An interest in preserving and protecting in situ archaeological sites must be taken in to account when publishing and distributing information about their nature and location.” This paper first provides a critical review of current geolocation sharing recommendations and practices, and then describes available methods for dealing with sensitive location data and suggested best practices. Particular attention is paid to geomasking techniques, which communicate observed spatial relationships while obscuring sensitive geographic coordinates. Currently, only two geomasking techniques are widely used in archaeology: aggregating archaeological site locations into grids or administrative units, or placing points that represent site locations at a particular distance from their true locations. These techniques, while useful, are part of a larger and growing suite of tools that visually convey spatial data without revealing sensitive site locations. Principle 6 allows researchers flexibility in tailoring methods of communicating site locations, which is useful given the range of archaeological contexts. However, this work encourages researchers to responsibly exercise that flexibility by incorporating archaeological and environmental data into an explicit decision-making process for representing those places.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="gis"></category><category term="sensitive-data"></category></entry><entry><title>Managing Digital Data at the North Carolina Office of State Archaeology: Challenges and Directions</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/nc-blewitt-abstract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Rosemarie Blewitt</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-02-19:/SAA2018digigovt/nc-blewitt-abstract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="rosemarie.blewitt@ncdcr.gov"&gt;Rosemarie Blewitt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The North Carolina Office of State Archaeology (OSA) was created by the North Carolina General Assembly in 1973 to coordinate and implement a statewide archaeological preservation program. Central to this program is the OSA’s management of records, including those documenting the more than 50,000 archaeological sites …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="rosemarie.blewitt@ncdcr.gov"&gt;Rosemarie Blewitt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The North Carolina Office of State Archaeology (OSA) was created by the North Carolina General Assembly in 1973 to coordinate and implement a statewide archaeological preservation program. Central to this program is the OSA’s management of records, including those documenting the more than 50,000 archaeological sites located in the state’s 100 counties, and a library of nearly 8,000 associated reports. The OSA Research Center curates tens of thousands of artifacts and their associated records from across North Carolina.
While there are computer databases for the site forms, bibliographic entries, maps, and artifacts, there is variability in the extent to which all records have been added to these databases. Arduous and labor intensive, the process of digitizing our records has evolved with the available technology and been limited by staffing. Our goal is to have this data in GIS and electronic databases accessible to researchers and easy to query. We will discuss our efforts to reach this goal and the potential benefits of digitizing our records.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="inventory"></category></entry><entry><title>Principles of Open Government Archaeology: Lessons from the Digital Index of North American Archaeology (DINAA)</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/open-wells-abstract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joshua J. Wells</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-02-19:/SAA2018digigovt/open-wells-abstract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;Joshua J. Wells&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American archaeology is conducted under cultural resources protection laws, but how does archaeology meet the challenge of openness? The past decade saw development of the “open government” digital information paradigm for public availability of information that underpins the functions of governance. Open government data provide a base …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;Joshua J. Wells&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American archaeology is conducted under cultural resources protection laws, but how does archaeology meet the challenge of openness? The past decade saw development of the “open government” digital information paradigm for public availability of information that underpins the functions of governance. Open government data provide a base for the interested public to offer expertise in aspects of necessary analyses, and to derive further public value from reuse of government data in novel ways. The open government concept has affected the practice and communication of scientific data in regulatory regimes as far flung as climate science, health science, and archaeology, among many others. In 2007 the “eight principles of open government” were coined by a group of public advocates, followed rapidly by a mosaic of federal, state, and local initiatives. The Digital Index of North American Archaeology (DINAA) is a completely free, big data, open government data project, centered at several public institutions; DINAA embodies open government practices to develop a novel linked-open data network of archaeological site primary data and related records across the internet. Our disciplinary capacity to engage with the principles of open government will be addressed through DINAA interoperability assessments and experiments with open government data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open-government"></category><category term="data"></category><category term="LOD"></category></entry></feed>