<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>SAA 2018 Government Digital Data - David Gadsby</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/feeds/david-gadsby.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/</id><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Approaches, Rationales, and Challenges to Maintaining Site Inventory in the National Parks</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/approaches-gadsby.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>David Gadsby</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-02-19:/SAA2018digigovt/approaches-gadsby.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="David_Gadsby@nps.gov"&gt;David Gadsby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, the National Park Service (NPS) has worked to preserve natural and cultural resources in more than four hundred park units for future generations.  In addition, the National Historic Preservation Act (NHPA) requires all federal agencies to maintain inventories of their historic properties.  For decades …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="David_Gadsby@nps.gov"&gt;David Gadsby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, the National Park Service (NPS) has worked to preserve natural and cultural resources in more than four hundred park units for future generations.  In addition, the National Historic Preservation Act (NHPA) requires all federal agencies to maintain inventories of their historic properties.  For decades, the NPS has relied upon three inventory systems: The List of Classified Structures, the Cultural Landscapes Inventory (CLI), and the Archeological Sites Management Information System (ASMIS). These systems began decades ago as paper files and continue today as electronic databases accessed via the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inventories allow NPS to maintain and update critical information including resource type, location, condition, threats, and disturbances.  As the relevant technologies continue to develop with what seems like increasing rapidity, even these relatively modern databases are being rapidly rendered obsolete.  The NPS Cultural Resources, Science, and Partnerships directorate has begun work to modernize these systems, and to facilitate their further integration with GIS technologies and other NPS programs, and incorporate elements of the now defunct Ethnographic Resources Inventory (ERI).  This paper discusses the issues faced as NPS updates these crucial tools for a second century of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gadsby Title Slide" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/2018/03/Gadsby_Slide1.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m David Gadsby. I work in the Cultural Resources, Science and Partnerships Office of the National Park Service, where I coordinate our inventory database of archeological resources. We’re currently working to modernize our inventory systems that track information about historic buildings, cultural landscapes, ethnographic resources and archeological sites, and streamline them into a new online system. You’re looking at the ruins of Casa Grande National Monument. The ruins date to 1400s, protected through citizen activism and presidential proclamation, 1892, declared a national monument in 1918. This is an archeological site -- CAGR00014,  with a subsite. The site includes historic and Hohokam features (incl. a drainage ditch excavated by Jesse Fewkes during 1906 stabilization).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also more than one historic structure LCS 06607(shelter) On the national register – Designed by Olmsted Co.  and Thomas Vint, 01044 (Compound A) (Classic Hohokam, Also on NR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a cultural landscape – including the visitor center, Casa Grande itself and surrounding vegetation plan – part of a master plan from the 1930s.&lt;br&gt;
In addition to buried archaeological deposits and standing structures, there are facilities (like the walkways) and interpretive signage, not to mention natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a park resource management perspective, this is a fairly complex situation, with a large number of resources and resource values packed into a relatively small physical space. It is also repeated at different scales and in different configurations across the seven regions and 417 national park units.  Creating a resource inventory system that meets NPS’s diverse and complex needs presents a number of challenges.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/SAA2018digigovt/images/2018/03/Gadsby_Slide2.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data"></category><category term="inventory"></category></entry><entry><title>Approaches, Rationales, and Challenges to Maintaining Site Inventory in the National Parks</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/approaches-gadsby-abstract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>David Gadsby</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-02-19:/SAA2018digigovt/approaches-gadsby-abstract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="David_Gadsby@nps.gov"&gt;David Gadsby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, the National Park Service (NPS) has worked to preserve natural and cultural resources in more than four hundred park units for future generations.  In addition, the National Historic Preservation Act (NHPA) requires all federal agencies to maintain inventories of their historic properties.  For decades …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="David_Gadsby@nps.gov"&gt;David Gadsby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a century, the National Park Service (NPS) has worked to preserve natural and cultural resources in more than four hundred park units for future generations.  In addition, the National Historic Preservation Act (NHPA) requires all federal agencies to maintain inventories of their historic properties.  For decades, the NPS has relied upon three inventory systems: The List of Classified Structures, the Cultural Landscapes Inventory (CLI), and the Archeological Sites Management Information System (ASMIS). These systems began decades ago as paper files and continue today as electronic databases accessed via the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inventories allow NPS to maintain and update critical information including resource type, location, condition, threats, and disturbances.  As the relevant technologies continue to develop with what seems like increasing rapidity, even these relatively modern databases are being rapidly rendered obsolete.  The NPS Cultural Resources, Science, and Partnerships directorate has begun work to modernize these systems, and to facilitate their further integration with GIS technologies and other NPS programs, and incorporate elements of the now defunct Ethnographic Resources Inventory (ERI).  This paper discusses the issues faced as NPS updates these crucial tools for a second century of service.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data"></category><category term="inventory"></category></entry></feed>