<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>SAA 2018 Government Digital Data - Jolene Smith</title><link href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/feeds/jolene-smith.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://127.0.0.1:8000/</id><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Always Halfway There: Keeping Up with Digital Archaeological Data in Virginia</title><link href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/halfway-smith-abstract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jolene Smith</name></author><id>tag:127.0.0.1,2018-02-19:/halfway-smith-abstract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="jolene.smith@dhr.virginia.gov"&gt;Jolene Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since being one of the first State Historic Preservation Offices to adopt electronic records management in the late ‘80s, the Virginia Department of Historic Resources has worked through several iterations of databases and web applications. These systems manage basic site information, details about physical collections, and now digital …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="jolene.smith@dhr.virginia.gov"&gt;Jolene Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since being one of the first State Historic Preservation Offices to adopt electronic records management in the late ‘80s, the Virginia Department of Historic Resources has worked through several iterations of databases and web applications. These systems manage basic site information, details about physical collections, and now digital media and datasets themselves. Over time, the agency’s priorities and objectives surrounding digital records and data have evolved in ways common to other institutions. As the most recent web GIS and database application reaches mid-life after four years, a thorough assessment of current and ideal approaches to digital data curation, preservation, and distribution is coming due as planning begins for what comes next. Building from concepts in libraries and archives, informatics, and data science, this presentation explores possible road maps.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data"></category><category term="inventory"></category></entry></feed>