<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>SAA 2018 Government Digital Data - Matthew McKnight</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/feeds/matthew-mcknight.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/</id><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>The Maryland Archaeological Synthesis Project: One State’s Solution to Archaeology’s Crushing Gray Literature Problem</title><link href="https://aejolene.github.io/SAA2018digigovt/synthesis-mcknight-abstract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Matthew McKnight</name></author><id>tag:aejolene.github.io,2018-02-19:/SAA2018digigovt/synthesis-mcknight-abstract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="matthew.mcknight@maryland.gov"&gt;Matthew McKnight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since passage of the National Historic Preservation Act fifty-two years ago a growing body of valuable data has been generated by state agencies, CRM professionals, and preservation officers. Unfortunately, this data is usually trapped in an archaic paper-based format, restricted geographically to a single state archive. All …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="matthew.mcknight@maryland.gov"&gt;Matthew McKnight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since passage of the National Historic Preservation Act fifty-two years ago a growing body of valuable data has been generated by state agencies, CRM professionals, and preservation officers. Unfortunately, this data is usually trapped in an archaic paper-based format, restricted geographically to a single state archive. All too often the data is brought to light only to be “reburied” in the SHPO’s library where it may be largely inaccessible to researchers scattered throughout the country. This paper describes how the Maryland Historical Trust is addressing this problem through the establishment of a secure, online, searchable catalog of raw data and CRM reports.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="CRM"></category><category term="gray-literature"></category></entry></feed>