<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>SAA 2018 Government Digital Data - Rachel Watson</title><link href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/feeds/rachel-watson.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://127.0.0.1:8000/</id><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Can you make me a map? Making Louisiana’s cultural resources records accessible</title><link href="http://127.0.0.1:8000/map-watson-abstract.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Rachel Watson</name></author><id>tag:127.0.0.1,2018-02-19:/map-watson-abstract.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="rwatson@crt.la.gov"&gt;Rachel Watson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper will outline the processes and decisions that the Louisiana Division of Archaeology made to create an efficient, comprehensive GIS system that could be utilized by both professionals and the citizenry of Louisiana to help promote both progress and preservation. I will discuss how we partnered with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="rwatson@crt.la.gov"&gt;Rachel Watson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper will outline the processes and decisions that the Louisiana Division of Archaeology made to create an efficient, comprehensive GIS system that could be utilized by both professionals and the citizenry of Louisiana to help promote both progress and preservation. I will discuss how we partnered with La Department of Transportation &amp;amp; Development, La Governor’s Office of Homeland Security &amp;amp; Emergency Preparedness, the New Orleans Corp Engineers, and the Federal Emergency Management Agency to fund the project.   Furthermore, I will discuss how we handled gaps in data and converting paper files into a digital format. Finally, I will outline future endeavors to raise public awareness of Louisiana’s rich cultural history utilizing open access maps, story boards, and applications for smartphones and tablets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="gis"></category><category term="sensitive-data"></category></entry></feed>